Introduction

This is an introduction to this template rather that Newlang, but you should feel free to make an introduction to Newlang instead.

Hopfully the prior paragraph is an obvious enough meta-comment in this template. The point of this document is to show how a constructed language could be documented. It tends to have as much as I can put into a section, with comments (like the prior paragraph) about how in-depth your constructed language is.

If you do a search on conlang.org you will find a list of language levels for paid conlangers. Before we get to actual language creation, we need to talk about the bug-a-boo of what some people think they are asking for when they ask for a constructed language; sadly this is even true in professional and very successful film franchises.

Vector Drawings

The goal here is to create artwork, for a grand total of somewhere between 25 and 30 glyphs. Generally because what we are doing here is actually creating a different way to write English. The reason we say between 25 and 30 rather than 26 is because we occasionally an additional symbol for /ʃ/ and /θ/ or /ð/ and are perhaps throwing away Q and X.

In addition to digital vector drawings of each glyph you should also provide one sentence in the created writing system.

For an idea of how you might document a set of glyphs, check out the chapter called "The Look of Newlang" and the section on "Orthography".

Digital Font

The goal here is to create a font that allows you to almost type English and look like a different language. It should have between 25 and 30 glyphs, though 26 is much more likely. We occasionally find things like Q or X serving as symbols for /ʃ/ and /θ/ or /ð/ or expect the typist to replace those letters with something more phonomic. Of course, modern fonts allow for quite a bit of freedom in having those additional symbols and occasionally the digits of zero through nine are also expected.

You should also provide instructions for installing and using the font.

For an idea of how you might document a font, check out the chapter called "The Look of Newlang" and the sections on "Orthography" and "Typing Newlang".

Now onto the real constructed languages.

Naming Language

A language created to provide a consistent naming structure for people and/or places.

You should also provide a phonology in addition to about two dozen names.

In general, neither drawings nor fonts will be made for a naming language. Names tend to be written in a modern othography regardless of the source language of the names. In the real world this gives us things like Onondaga in New York while you find Tulalip in Washington.

Conlang Sketch

This is something more appropriate for a language used in limited circumstances; like official decrees, magic incantations, or barked orders on a starship.

You should provide a simplified grammar; we're talking subject-verb-object word order. You will also need to provide a dictionary of about fifty words.

One thing that may be wanted along with a conlang sketch is a unique way to write it. Making a whole font is probably overkill for a limited language used in limited circumstances. But some digital vector drawings may be wanted along with one sentence fully rendered in images, so be clear.

Basic Conlang

This is supposed to be enough of a language that you can actually make some dialogue.

At a minimum this should include: phonology, a basic grammar, five to ten sample sentences translated, and a dictionary of about 150 words.

This does not necessarily mean a unique writing system. The first question to ask yourself is if you even want a unique writing system for it. Perhaps literacy is low enough that it doesn't make sense, maybe it's a language that lacks prestige.

If you do want to write it, then you must decide if you want images, which are easier to make but harder to string into sentences; or a font, which is harder to make but easier to string into sentences. Either way be clear about expectations.

Advanced Grammar

As much as possible, this template has tried to provide what is needed to make an advanced grammar.

This will include at least: a phonology, a full grammar (questions, multiple clauses, etc.), between 20 and 30 sentences translated and a dictionary of at least 500 words.

Just like with a basic conlang, this may not necessarily include a writing system. Do you even want a unique writing system for it. Perhaps they haven't invented writing yet, maybe it's considered too sacred to write down.

If you do want to write it, then you will want to make a font and add a rendering of the 20 to 30 translations using the font but have clarity about the creation or non-creation of a font.

What Now?

Now that we have explained the different levels, you will find boxes throughout this document just like at the beginning of this chapter that will point out things like this chapter isn't used in a naming language, or this section is only for an advanced grammar.

In each case I've tried to include a large sample of what can be, so that you can focus on being creative.

Enjoy.

Description of Newlang

A full description of Newlang is as follows.

Morphology and Syntax

Newlang is full of inflections that permit some freedom in word order but the default structure of Newlang is head final, subject-verb-object. Newlang is an agglutinating language. Genitives follow nouns and the word de, adpositions are called prepositions because they precede their clauses, and nouns must precede their relative clauses. Finally, even though Newlang is head-final, adverbs follow their verbs.

The red bird quickly went to the dog's house.

would be

The red bird went quickly to house of the dog.

If you are doing a language sketch, then this may be enough. Proceed with caution.

Nouns

Newlang nouns inflect for number, case, gender, possesion, ...

Noun cases are: actor, patient, or broker and these functions/cases are identified by adding/changing/removing ...

Noun numbers are: singular, dual, plural, non-zero, fractional, ...

Noun genders are: animate, inanimate, fey, ...

Adjectives

Newlang adjectives (dis)agree with their nouns but only in case and number. They are further inflected for evidence.

Because of the agreement with their nouns, adjectives can come before or after but they are most often placed before. Adjectives must come before the nouns they modify. If there are multiple adjectives they are placed in order of place, time, and color.

Adjective numbers are: singular and plural. If the attached noun is dual, the adjective is marked for singular.

Adjective evidences are: seen and heard.

Demonstratives

All Newlang demonstratives are deictic and are inflected only for gender.

tie means that place (there) and is inherently inanimate.

tiu means that animate thing.

tius means that inanimate thing.

Verbs

Newlang verbs conjugate for tense and believability and must (dis)agree with their adverbs. Copulas are formed by using an adjective as the object of the present tense of the verb esti; la birdo estas ruja means "the bird is blue". Negation is handled by replacing all the vowels with a so la birdo ne astas ruja means "the bird isn't blue".

The tenses are: past, present, future, unlikely, by dictate of the gods, ... Past tense is created by adding t before the verb.

Adverbs

Adverbs must follow the verb they modify and are of three types: manner, location, and time.

Manner adverbs are formed by taking an adjective and inflecting it with a following e: mi iris rapide "I went quickly".

Time adverbs are unique words:

a means long time ago.

Unless you are doing an Advanced Grammar, the chapter is almost over. A Basic Grammar should skip the next several sections and finish the chapter with the historical notes.

Participles

Participles come in two basic forms: active, meaning that the subject is doing the verb that the participle is based on; passive, meaning that the subject is having the verb done to them that the participle is based on.

Both types of participles inflect for tense and number: vidinta means "was seeing", ...

Coordination

Conjunctions are handled by using the preposition: ka means and, ...

Relative Clauses

A relative clause as the subject//noun is formed by iirect object/indirect object/adposition/possessive

Questions

Yes/no questions, that expect the answer to be agreement, are formed by taking a statement and changing ...

Yes/no questions, that expect the answer to be dis-agreement, are formed by taking a statement and ...

Questions asking for information are formed by taking a statemend and replacing the subject/object with one of the following words: it meaning a place "where", ...

Historical Notes

Even if you are only making a basic grammar, you should include this section, unless your language is a priori.

Below is a behind-the-scenes description of the historical processes that gave rise to the current alternations seen in Newlang. In the descriptions below, a segment, word or phrase preceded by an asterisk (*) is a proto-form. A proto-form is an older form that's no longer present in the modern language. The changes are listed in order.

Loss of Schwa: *ǝ > Ø / \_,G

The basic schwa was lost next to glides and the glottal stop. These sounds affected a change in the surrounding vowels, resulting in modern i, u, and a, as well as older *ai and *au.

...

Introduction to the Newlang Dictionary

The fourth item explained here should only be present if you are also providing a font. The fifth item explained here should only be present if you are also providing vector drawings or a font.

Below is a sample dictionary entry from the Newlang to English side of the dictionary. Each item has a number which corresponds to an explanation below the entry:

wordi^1 [word.'i]^2 *wrd^3 cxhxsxux^4 cxhxsxux^5 {24}*^6 (v.)^7 to gloss^8 (nice note)^9

Citation Form: Newlang words will be listed by the citation form. This is the basic romanized form that will be used in scripts and translations. When preparing artwork, the Orthographic Form should be used, in which case the Typographic Form should be followed closely to produce an accurate result.

Phonetic Form: This is how the word is pronounced. The transcription will be written in IPA, and will be more or less phonetic (unimportant details being left out). You'll notice in this example that the citation form and the phonetic form do match fairly closely, as intended by the romanization system.

Etymology: This is the etymology for each word. It will prove crucial in derived languages. In Newlang it's more or less a repetition of the information already provided.

Typographic Form: This is exactly what you type to produce the Newlang forms in the Orthographic Form using the provided font.

Orthographic Form: This is how the word will look in the orthography of the native Newlang writing system.

Word Type: This system identifies how common a given word is and whether or not it's impolite. It also identifies words that may be interesting examples to share. The system is as follows:

{X...}: The first digit is a measure of how well known the word is.

1: Indicates that this word is so basic to the language it is difficult to understand without these words. For English this would be things like pronouns. Even utterances like "me Jane, you John" will require an understanding of these. For Newlang this also includes some ...

2: Indicates basic words that either affect meaning in ways not obvious or considered a basic part of interacting. Things like asking for information, or "What's this called?".

3: Indicates words that are common and likely to be used by all people in most situations. If a native doesn't know this word, they can probably guess it from context. This is the default word type.

4: Indicates words that are either a less used synonym or words only used is special contexts like riddles or other wordplay. May also be words that are no longer part of the language but used to be an can still be found in idioms like the English "to and fro".

5: Indicates words that are technical but may be generally known. If it is known the generally understood meaning may be different than the technical meaning like doctor's referring to a condition as "chronically acute".

{...X}: The second digit is a measure of how polite the word is.

1: Indicates words that are both crude and offensive. These words can lead to fights and even start wars.

2: Indicates words that are crude but not necessarily offensive. In some contexts these words may no longer be considered crude. Sometimes that context is situational, like when visiting a specialist. Sometimes it is based on relationships, just like some things you can say to close friends that may be rude otherwise.

3: Indicates words that are neutral and usable in any situation. This is the default type.

4: Indicates that this is considered a polite word to use. In English "please" and "thank you" would be this level.

5: Indicates words that are considered cumpulsory for basic politeness. If you fail to use these words you may offend.

{...}*: An asterisk attached to the type indicates that the word is unique or interesting enough to pay attention to. It may be a word that plays a crucial role in the lore of the world or that has a bizarre etymology. The asterisk following the curly bracket makes these words easy to search for.

Part of Speech: The part of speech refers to the Newlang part of speech, and not the English part of speech. If a word fits more than one part of speech, it is listed more than once. The list of Newlang parts of speech is:

(det.) = determiner.

(n.) = noun.

Definition: Some words will have single word definitions, others a semantic description, and some will have multiple definitions. If it is a single word definition we may provide some semantic conditions for this meaning.

Extra Information: Extra information will appear in parentheses. The extra information is there to give the reader a clearer idea of exactly how the word is used. Often socio-cultural information about a given word will appear in parentheses.

The Look of Newlang

Newlang has a distinctive look as described here.

Transcription

The symbols listed in the tables of the previous chapter are phonetic symbols. These will be used to transcribe Newlang words, but not to write them. To write them, we utilize a romanization system that should make the pronunciation fairly transparent. That transcription system is listed below:

The following sounds will be written using the same letter as their phonetic symbol: m, n, p, b, t, d, k, g, q, ts, dz, f, v, s, z, h, l, w, i, u, e, o, ǝ, and a.

The sounds [tʃ] (kind of like the "ch" in "charge") will be spelled ch.

The sounds [dʒ] (kind of like the "j" in "jar") will be spelled j.

The sound [ʝ] (similar to the "z" in "azure") will be spelled zh.

The sound [ɖ] (no English equivalent) will be spelled d.

The sounds [ɟ] and [ʝ] (kind of like the "j" in "jar") will be spelled j.

The sounds [ɣ] and [ʁ] (no English equivalent) will be spelled gh.

Long vowels will be written with a doubled version of the vowel (so [iː] will be written ii).

Make sure you cover every sound you have identified in the prior chapter.

Romanization

This is the romanization system, which will be used to spell Newlang using the Roman alphabet. This is also how to find Newlang words in the Newlang dictionary. The full system is described in detail here:

A, a: Pronounced like the "a" in "father".

A, a: Pronounced like the "a" in "father", but held slightly longer.

B, b: Pronounced like the "b" in "bad".

Ch, ch: Pronounced like the "ch" in "each". Unlike the sound "ch" in English "chair", there is no discernible puff of air that accompanies this sound. If one holds one's breath while pronouncing the "ch" in English "chair", one will pronounce this sound correctly.

G, g: Pronounced like the "g" in "goat" (never like the "g" in "genius").

H, h: Pronounced like the "h" in "hat". If this letter is preceded by another letter that may imply a different pronounciation a small dot (•) will be placed between the letters to indicate two separate consonants.

K', k': There's no English equivalent to this sound. This is an ejective consonant. In the case of k', it's pronounced just like k, but with one's breath held. The result is a little "popping" sound that immediately follows the production of the k. You can think of it as a k that's followed by a glottal ' sound. Producing those two sounds in short succession will result in a sound very close to k'. Continue to practice and you should be able to get it.

One Important Note Regarding Double Consonants: If a digraph (e.g. kh, gh, etc.) is doubled, only the first letter will be doubled (hence, kkh not khkh). The consonant is pronounced like a doubled consonant, though, as actual combinations such as k followed by kh are impossible.

Make sure you cover every sound you have in the dictionary indexes.

Orthography

This section is only included if you are providing either vector images or a font. Otherwise you need to say something along the lines of "Newlang has a unique orthography used to write it but we will continue to use the romanization system as described above for ease and simplicity." or even "Newlang does not have an orthography because ..."

Newlang has a unique orthography used to write it. The orthography of Newlang consists of an alphabet/abjad/abudiga/syllabary/logogram/mixed system with two/three cases. These two cases are called maiusklo and minusklo but they correspond to our upper case and lower case letters. The upper case is used for names, places, and nouns otherwise the lower case is used.

Symbols are written left to right and lines move from the top of the page to the bottom. When written right to left the shapes will be mirrored. It is understood to consist of twenty-eight letters (called literoi and which also means ...), though it really consists of twenty-two letters and two diacritical marks added to a small sub-set of the twenty-two letters.

If there are a lot of spelling exceptions, make sure to mention that here.

a is indicated by the upper case symbol A or the lower case symbol a which sometimes has the alternative form of a.

b is indicated by the upper case symbol B or the lower case symbol b.

ch is indicated by the upper case symbol Cx or the lower case symbol cx.

dz is indicated by the digraph dz.

g is indicated by the upper case symbol G or the lower case symbol g, but Newlang has a long tradition of printing which uses the lower case symbol g and most native charts will show g even most people will write g.

i following a or o (both dipthongs) is indicated by the lower j, but in all other cases is indicated by the upper case symbol I or the lower case symbol i.

ts is indicated by the upper case symbol C or the lower case symbol c.

u following a, e, o (dipthongs) is indicated by the upper case symbol Ux or the lower case symbol ux, but in all other cases is indicated by the upper case symbol U or the lower case symbol u.

This format works well for alphabets and some abjads.

For some abjads as well as some abugidas a consonant and vowel section will probably be needed.

For some abugidas and syllabaries a table will probably be needed.

For logograms and mixed systems, go wild!

A basic pronunciation chart would look like:

A a
a

|

B b
b

|

C c
ts

|

Cx cx
ch

|

D d
d

E e
e

|

F f
f

|

G g
g

|

Gx gx
gh

|

H H
h

Hx hx
kh

|

I i
i

|

J j
y or i

|

Jx jx
zh

|

K k
k

L l
l

|

M m
m

|

N n
n

|

O o
o

|

P p
p

R r
r

|

S s
s

|

Sx Sx
sh

|

T t
t

|

U u
u

Ux ux
u

|

V v
v

|

Z z
z

Typing Newlang

In case you are curious, this font happens to be a cut-down and slightly modified FreeSerif.ttf.

The font file is called NewLangRegular.otf. Before you can use it, you will need to install it. In almost all modern operating systems, installation consists of double-clicking on the file, seeing a preview of the font, and clicking on a button with the word "Install" on it. Once you have accomplished that, close out of all your word processors and restart them to ensure that they know the font is available. You should now see a font named NewLangRegular.

The correspondence between the romanization and the sounds of Newlang has influenced the method of typing in this alphabet. The symbol of the left is the symbol typed if you hold the shift key down while pressing that key and the symbol on the right is the symbol typed if you do not hold the shift key down. If we consider the typical qwerty keyboard, then the layout is as follows:

Q

|

W

|

E
E e

|

R
R r

|

T
T t

|

Y

|

U
U u

|

I
I i

|

O
O o

|

P
P p

A
A a

|

S
S s

|

D
D d

|

F
F f

|

G
G g

|

H
H h

|

J
J j

|

K
K k

|

L
L l

Z
Z z

|

X
^

|

C
C c

|

V
V v

|

B
B b

|

N
N n

|

M
M m

The lowercase x key is used to add a compatible accent the the base character. Uppercase X will not work. If you want to see either a Cx or a Ux you need to type Cx or Ux.

Many spellings are based on historic pronunciations or borrowings and will not follow the general rules. The dictionary will show the current spelling, the way to type it using this font, and the modern pronounciation.